In 2017,
Studio MDHR released Cuphead,
one of the best games I’ve ever played.
It’s a 2D animated run and gun action game
where you defeat around 20 bosses
so that you can gain soul contracts and also beat the Devil.
The unique thing and what I was drawn to when I first saw this game
was the look or animation of it.
It’s based on “rubber hose” animations from the 1930s
with every frame being hand drawn
and then scanned onto a computer to color it and then code it,
which is just next level.
Nice job team!
Since 2017, Studio MDHR also released a DLC called the “Delicious Last Course”.
Haha, get it?
And it’s also pretty good, adding more weapons and charms to the game.
As for the gameplay, it’s pretty fun,
but it gets pretty challenging at times because there’s a lot going on screen
and you have to use the right amount of skill to dodge attacks.
I’ve even heard people compare this game to Dark Souls for some reason.
You can play the game as Mugman or Ms. Chalice if you have the DLC
and you can also play the game in 2 player mode with a friend as well.
Cuphead is one of my top 5 games out there
and I give it a 10/10 just because I personally love it.
It’s an amazing game with an old-ish artstyle,
a really good musical score,
and engaging gameplay that I can never get bored of.
Seriously, go check it out if you haven’t,
and there’s also a Netflix show about it too which is pretty neat.
Now with anything that’s popular,
there’s always gonna be copies of it,
and Cuphead is no different.
The first clone of Cuphead I heard about is “Enchanted Portals”.
This is a game marketed as being Cuphead inspired,
being the most popular clone of Cuphead with people still referencing it to this day.
As for the plot,
it’s about 2 Harry Potter wizards accidentally stumbling upon a book,
they cast spells on it,
and then they get sucked into another world and fight bosses.
Now I have never played the game, but looking at reviews of it on YouTube,
the art is pretty nice but the game just doesn't feel as polished and as smooth as Cuphead is.
3 out of 10.
“Rubber Hose Rampage” is another game that comes to mind.
I found this game because of a Pogobro and boy oh boy is it bad.
The game is in black and white,
the animation isn’t smooth,
and most of it is traced on really old cartoons anyways.
Some bosses are impossible to beat, and it just screams poor quality.
The game did get updated by adding more bosses and color into the game,
but it’s still a piece of garbage.
1 out of 10.
CHICKEN JOCKEY
God Bless The USA
It's time for the moment you've been waiting for!
Duh...
Duh (x7)
Duh (x15)
I don't want to sub all this, you know the point.
Spongebob Seasons 1-3 was peak.
Alvin and the Chipmunks
I feel like P Diddy with fur
Preparing...
“Toyland Tussle”.
This is probably the best Cuphead clone ever and hence why I wanted to make this video.
I found this because of Shaconda Cartoons, a channel I’m subscribed to
and honestly, it looks pretty good.
This game was released to Steam,
because every video game ever is on Steam,
in August 2025 which is last month.
The developer is RBW games
and the price of it is 3 dollars.
Needless to say, I bought the game to see how it was and…
Nah I’m just kidding.
I got it from a quacked site because I don’t have any money right now, but anyways…
When you first start the game, it opens up in windowed view,
so now I have to push P to fullscreen it.
Which is pretty annoying, but it's a minor inconvenience.
In the main menu,
I didn't know which button to press to select the items, so I used my controller.
This game has controller support btw and it's fine.
Eventually, I found out that you press the ‘spacebar’ to select the items and ‘enter’ to go back.
Anyways, the stats menu allows you to change the film to a ‘color’ or a ‘black and white’ filter,
and a menu to view the guns.
Press ‘A’ on your controller and ‘enter’ on your keyboard to go back to the main menu.
The controls menu tells you which button to press and you can change it to another preset.
Unfortunately it doesn't let you rebind or remap the keys,
you are stuck at whatever the game gives you.
Pressing play gives you the difficulty of standard or extreme,
and whichever one you click,
it will showcase you the plot of the story.
So as a plot goes,
the main character is called “Fodder the Cannon”.
He was walking downtown wanting to spend his money on something,
then he saw a small toystore and proceeded to walk inside.
In the store, there's a music box on a pedestal and because of curiosity,
he decided to open the box and then he got sucked into a world made of toys.
He gets jumpscared by this monkey or whatever, and then the game starts.
So here is the boss!
This game only has one boss battle
and it doesn't have a name so I don't know what to call this.
In the first phase, you fight the guy who just jumpscared you.
He does 3 attacks and it's either:
a streak of lightning across the floor,
the clapping of his symbols,
or music notes that falls down.
When you die, there's a death screen, saying:
"Ha! I knew you would lose, even if there was a hundred of you's!”
Probably a reference to the 100 men vs 1 gorilla thing.
And it gives you the option to retry the level,
exit to the main menu,
or equip another weapon.
Speaking of which,
there are four weapons, being the:
bullet, firework, bounce bomb, and splitter.
The bullet is the first weapon that you get.
It's basically just like the peashooter in Cuphead,
shooting in a straight line and it's EX is a bigger bullet.
The firework is like the chaser in Cuphead,
it homes onto the enemy but with the EX being a ring moving in a circular pattern.
This one has the least amount of damage at 1.
The bounce bomb reminds me of the lobber but it shoots across the screen
and it's EX is 6 bigger bombs bouncing across the screen.
This has the most amounts of damage at 4
Finally the splitter,
it shoots in both the front and back of your head and the EX is 2 bigger spears.
Not sure why you would need this weapon though.
In the second phase, you deal with two monkeys that either:
spits out peanuts from their mouth,
throw a coconut that splits into 2 pieces,
or throw out their head that bounces from the floor back to them.
There's even a banana that walks across the screen to make it even harder.
Embarrassingly, I died a lot on this phase because there was so much stuff going on
and I couldn't dodge quick enough.
Even as the chimpanzees, they can see that I'm the real monkey.
But after a couple of tries, I got to phase 3.
In phase 3, the monkey from the start reveals himself in a bigger form
and he does 3 attacks once again.
Stretching his hand out to punch me,
shooting barrels into the sky that falls down,
or a banana that shoots in 6 directions
that you have to dodge very quick before you lose your health.
Eventually, I got to beat him,
or maybe he beats himself,
and I got a bronze ranking!
Apparently this guy is nice and I just beat him up for no reason.
I take a walk into a portal,
get sucked back to reality,
somebody screams at me to get away,
and I learned a very valuable lesson that day.
Spelled wrong by the way.
And that was it, only one boss!
In the credits screen,
we learn that RBW stands for Raz Bennett-Warner,
and this person did all work on the game, which is impressive.
He thanks his family and friends and then us for playing the game.
You're welcome.
And that's it!
I give my compliments to the chef.
As for what I like about Toyland Tussle,
the animation is pretty good.
It looks like it’s based on Cuphead with it having the same style and the old grainy filter.
Unlike the other clones,
the animation is pretty smooth and polished,
and I personally haven't found any bugs yet.
The music and sound effects are fine,
you can view the OST on the Official YouTube channel.
I feel like it can be improved,
but I'm not a game developer
and I'll cut RBW some slack because it's only one person behind it.
Gameplay wise, it's pretty fun and challenging to play
and somewhat difficult just like Cuphead.
I like the attacks that the bosses give you and it's pretty creative.
For things that I don't like however,
it sucks that you can't rebind your keys.
Doing that would probably help me defeat the bosses easier by keeping my muscle memory.
There's just no option.
Speaking of that, there's no settings in the game either.
You can't change your resolution or volume level like in other games.
Another pet peeve that I have is that the game doesn't tell me what to press,
like “spacebar” to select or “enter” to the pause screen.
Speaking of which,
there's no resume button so I kept replaying the boss on accident.
There's also no tutorial on how to play the game for newcomers.
But most people know this game as the “Cuphead Clone”
and most people already know how Cuphead works.
Finally, there's only one boss battle in the game,
with nothing else to explore and it can get pretty boring after a while.
Besides that,
this game has a lot of potential being a very good fan-game or clone to Cuphead,
and if the developer ever updates an adds more stuff in the game,
I'll definitely replay it in the future.
We will watch your career with great interest.
As for my rating,
I'll give it a 7 out of 10 because it’s pretty decent
but it only has 1 boss.
It’s probably the best Cuphead clone I’ve ever seen.
No game comes close to this.
Looking back at the script,
I forgot to mention Acecraft.
The game is good,
the bosses are pretty cool
and it has somewhat of a storyline,
but it’s only for mobile and it has some micro-transactions,
so I’ll give it a 6 out of 10.
But yeah,
Toyland Tussle has a lot of potential
and I hope there are more developments to the game.
Go check it out if you haven’t,
and I’ll see you next time.
Bye!
Me after getting 99 instead of 100 on test.